I'm Saurav.
This is D3Recovery and it was developed
at the X-ray and Emission Imaging Lab at Weill Cornell Medicine.
This is our Prism-PET 1 scanner.
It has 40 detector blocks to detect the gamma ray emission from the human brain.
Our PET detector block has a 16 × 16 crystal array and an 8 × 8 SiPM grid,
with a 4-to-1 crystal-to-SiPM coupling ratio.
This figure visually illustrates the first interaction in an inter-crystal scatter event,
from here on also called ICS event.
The 3D position of the first interaction in an ICS event,
comprising crystal ID and the depth of interaction,
are essential for PET scan reconstruction.
Hence, identifying both accurately is the goal of this work.
In a photoelectric event, as there is only one interaction site,
it's relatively easy to identify the first interaction crystal.
On the right, the observed SiPM pattern is our source or input to the framework.
However, first interaction crystal identification is challenging
in an ICS SiPM pattern due to multiple interaction sites.
We found in our Prism-PET 1 experiments
that about 70 to 80% events are these challenging ICS events.
In the 511 keV photon energy zone, where gamma radiation operates,
Compton scattering is often observed, giving rise to more ICS events.
Across crystals and depths, the photoelectric SiPM patterns vary significantly.
Hence, a similar variation is also expected in ICS events.
Using the center of gravity, or the CoG method,
it is easy to locate the first interaction crystal in a photoelectric event.
However, due to contamination, CoG fails significantly in an ICS event.
LOR, shorthand for line of response,
may also get affected due to mispositioning error in ICS events.
Mispositioning errors accumulate per event and compromise the scan resolution.
Our previous work, called Recovery-Net, uses a convolutional neural net
with two branches for crystal ID and DOI prediction, with the ICS SiPM pattern as input.
While it achieves decent performance, it only uses simulated data for training,
lacking experimental SiPM patterns from the scanner.
To further improve the first interaction position recovery,
what if we first recover the SiPM pattern?
By its nature, this task can be modeled as an image-to-image problem.
Such a problem is involved, as it is not easy to perform recovery
using conventional methods on an ICS pattern with overlapping interactions, as shown.
This plot shows that majority of the ICS events have such overlapping interactions.
Thus, we model the recovered distribution to be probabilistic,
and we use a conditional diffusion model for this task.
First interaction pattern and 10,240 total crystals are the two primary challenges
in this data acquisition process.
Since an ICS event consists of more than one interaction,
it can be viewed as multiple photoelectric patterns summed with energy weights.
For many crystals, a collimated source
would have to be passed through every crystal to get such data.
This is a time-consuming process.
Thanks to our previous work, we have a photoelectric patterns dataset per crystal per DOI
from a cylinder phantom experiment.
We perform GATE simulation that yields crystal ID and DOI
for every interaction of an ICS event.
Using these, we find an experimental photoelectric pattern,
which is weighted using the simulated energy.
A weighted sum of these patterns results in a synthetic ICS SiPM pattern,
which is the input to our framework.
And the first interaction pattern, crystal ID and DOI are our target variables.
We propose a novel framework called D3Recovery
that stands for diffusion-driven tripartite recovery.
Stage 1 is a conditional diffusion model that takes Gaussian noise,
the ICS SiPM pattern and block ID embeddings,
which encode the detector geometry, as input.
Forward diffusion is carried out by adding incremental noise
at each time step to the ground truth first interaction SiPM pattern.
Then, the reverse diffusion process takes place by denoising the Gaussian noise,
and a U-Net is used for this process.
These are some results from this Stage 1 diffusion model.
We benchmarked the CoG method using the recovered predicted patterns,
showing significant improvement in CoG.
However, diffusion is an image-to-image framework.
Our goal is 3D position.
Additionally, what if pattern recovery is incorrect?
Stage 1 also lacks the ICS and first interaction correlation,
as this may result in further improvement.
Hence, we propose Stage 2 for accurate position recovery.
Using the recovered and ICS SiPM patterns, along with the block ID embeddings, as input,
we develop a physics-informed CrystalAttentionNet,
comprising cross-attention and 16 × 16 spatial probability heat map prediction head,
as opposed to a classification head in Recovery-Net for crystal ID prediction.
We also have a guided depth model for DOI recovery,
which uses crystal ID as a regularizer during training.
These are event-level results with Stage 1 and Stage 2 predictions.
In the highlighted case,
we see that Stage 2 is accurate even when Stage 1 prediction is incorrect,
due to including both patterns in the input.
We also show some rare failure cases,
where Stage 1 is correct but Stage 2 is wrong, or both stages are wrong.
At the event level, we evaluate D3Recovery with center of gravity,
Recovery-Net, center of gravity with Stage 1 baselines
for crystal ID and DOI error width at full width half maximum.
Crystal prediction distance is also another metric.
In all the above, our framework performs the best.
At the scan level, we can validate the improvement visually,
particularly in the shown region, from a 3D ultra-Derenzo phantom experiment.
A baseline comparison is presented.
Quantitatively, we observe a 24% peak-to-valley ratio improvement
using D3Recovery for this phantom experiment.
In this 3D Hoffman brain phantom experiment,
we observe significant improvements in the certain regions as shown.
We document the structural similarity index,
mean absolute error and standard deviation for all the methods.
In conclusion, we propose a practical experiment dataset generation method,
a novel physics-informed D3Recovery framework that achieves superior performance
in ICS recovery as compared to the analytical and CNN baseline methods.
Our future work, called D3RecoveryMux, will focus on interleaved multiplexing
using flow-matching diffusion model to further improve ICS recovery.
Thanks to our principal investigator, Dr. Amir Goldan,
Dr. Wanbin Tan, and all my team members.
Thank you for watching.